here
everyone so nice to meet you. My name
is Andrew Lee and I'm a product designer a notion.
So quick show of hands. How many of you have used
notion I've heard of it before.
We're cool a good amount of people so over
the next 30 minutes. I love
to talk to you all about three things first is
notion the product and it's Primitives.
Second is our design approach as a team.
And then lastly I want to do a deep dive of one
of our projects.
But before I go into this, I want
to start the day with the story.
a story about tools and
the future of work
So if you're like me, you're probably in front of a computer all day
and you might have a couple
dozen tabs open right maybe one for email another for
slack figma maybe
but kind of have you ever asked yourself. Why is
it that in 2022? This is
the main way that we work, right? What's the origin story
of these tools?
So to answer this question and to answer this question of why we
built notion we have to travel back in time.
So let's rewind the scene to a hundred
fifty years ago. And let's imagine
what the world felt like right my trip
to New York would have taken a month.
Life expectancy wasn't so
high. So apologies to those over 40 and Communications
was quite primitive,
right the first prototype of the telephone had just
been invented.
And if we kind of shift gears into the work setting
what ended up happening was people flocked into
the first office setting and in
this environment two tools emerged.
The first tool was the typewriter. So this
standardized handwritten documents and streamlined that
process.
And the second tool was the file cabinet. It allowed
you to organize these documents to add
more structure to reference them. Later.
And if we kind of fast forward to the 1950s, this
is when the first computer was introduced and
the first computers weren't really that great. There
were these giant room size machines. It
was mainly for technicians scientists
military people and you
would think that a machine like this would change the way we work fundamentally, but
actually not much changed.
And it was in the 70s that a group of
computer Pioneers emerged onto the scene and they
really questioned the status quo.
What happens if we take the computing power of this
machine and intersected that with human
creativity?
What if we used computers to augment human intelligence?
It's a super interesting question and folks like
Ted Nelson Alan Kay Douglas engelbarth.
These were the folks that kind of set the
foundation for computing that we know today.
But something got Lost in Translation, right? You
would think that these ideas would kind of disrupt fundamentally
the way we work. But actually if
you think about the tools that we use today, they're quite
rigid and conceptually, they're very similar to the typewriter
and the file cabinet right? If you think about a document
editor, it's a typewriter in pixels,
maybe in the cloud and same goes for the file
database file cabinets.
And this is where notion comes in we really want
to break away from this this Paradigm
of working in rigid Silo tools.
Why not have a single tool
for all your needs rather than working in
these disparate tools, and we really want to revive the
ideas of these early Computing pioneers.
So that's what notion is. It's an all-in-one tool.
for documents wikis projects and
tasks
But it's also much more than that. It's it's a flexible system a single
canvas that you could build on top of.
And so that's our mission a notion is to make software
at school making ubiquitous for everyone.
And so in order to achieve our mission, our product
has to be amazing.
And if you haven't opened notion, this is what
it looks like when you first open it.
It's simple.
It's approachable.
It's pretty familiar. It feels like a text editor, right?
So you might start typing and add some text.
Maybe an image or two and kind of
format your page.
Emojis, our customers love emojis and soon
enough the documents slowly comes
to life from this blank canvas into a much
more Dynamic document.
You could add some structure where you can then filter and
search and soon enough. You have
these much more first class use cases, maybe one
for a docs and Wiki.
Maybe another for managing your projects.
And the amazing thing is all this happens in a single
environment.
So rather than me sending an email to Georgia
at 3 am about my keynote presentation, she and
I can operate in a single environment in a
in a single workspace.
So that's kind of the the magic behind notion.
And the reason why notion is so
flexible is because everything is built on this
primitive called a block.
So a block in notion you can think of it
as a container of information. It could be text. It
could be an image. It can be a video but it could also be so much
more. It could be real data that
you can integrate from external sources. It could be code. It
could be a quote block really the
possibilities are endless and the mental model
that we have. Is that of Lego
In the most primitive most foundational layer, you
have these individual blocks that anyone can kind
of play with an interact with and explore.
But on the other hand of the spectrum you can build these blocks into something
much more opinionated something much more structured like
a Lego set.
I think there's a speaker later from the LEGO Group. So quick
shout out. We're big fans of Lego from
from the ocean.
So this is what notion looks like in motion. It's
a flexible canvas, you
can move around and drag around these blocks and the
mental model is quite similar to maybe that of
a desktop computer. You can drag and
drop you can select multiple elements and we
want to notion to feel as familiar and intuitive as
possible even though at in the very beginning it might
feel like a simple text editor.
I would do is you could.
Turn blocks into other blocks. So here you have a
code block and you could turn that into a quote block.
Move it around.
Put it place it into another part of the
app.
So that's notion in a nutshell. It's a super
flexible tool.
But you might kind of Wonder as as a
design team a design team of sixth. How
do we design this product?
So
In order to answer that question. I want to take I wanted
to take a quick poll of the room. So I think most of
us are designers here. So if given the
task which design problem would you
rather solve?
Would you rather build the perfect chair and
bring that to markets you might think of the
curves you might think about this more intuitively and more tactically
or would you
want to build a built environment a city or a town?
Perhaps the problems are obviously much more
complex and night and day but a quick show
of hands whose team chair.
Okay, not many people and who
would rather build the city?
Wow, okay.
That's that's awesome. So it seems like more people prefer the
the city.
So yeah for the chair the designer might
think about much more intuitive and tactical things
like the materials the the cost
of the chair. How do you assemble it?
How comfortable is it? And these are very localized problems
that something that a team can very intuitively solve
you really caring about the craft of the problem right
and maybe if you make a mistake you
have always next year to iterate on that.
But if you think about the city as a problem,
it's a much more complex problem. Right? It's actually
not a single problem. It's a network of complex nodes
and you're thinking about all sorts of things from transits to
the general environment Healthcare so
many complex systems that come into place
that it would be impossible for a single designer to intuitively
solve for
And if we kind of map this on a chart you can
see that well the chair shape problem the answer
the form and the solution to it is much more
straightforward. But if you kind of extend the
Spectrum and think about the city problem the
solution is actually not that straightforward there
might require a lot
of exploration and Christopher Alexander talks about
this concept achieving Fitness between context
which is the setting of
your problem and form, which is the solution
to that problem.
And he talks about how good design isn't actually just the
solution or the form on its own but it's actually this
Ensemble between how how
a solution fits in with the
original context.
So let's extend that to notion. And this
is how notion product designers operate conceptually
we float between these these differently
shaped problems from chair-shaped problems
to City shape problems. So very tactically a
cherished problem might look
something like this where customers have
wrote into us and they really Express
the need to have more controls over their
images. So the solution in return is quite
simple. There's there's some execution
obviously involved but really the solution here is
to allow customers to
kind of align their images maybe sensor left, right and it's
a relatively simple design problem and it's actually still
quite important customers love notion because
we ship these smaller features that that they
love
But on the other end of the spectrum if we take the city shape
problem. Another notion problem is that customers actually
don't realize the use
cases for notion. So the benefit of notion is that
it's flexible. It's powerful but for first-time
users, they're quite confused. What is
the main use case? And so to think about this problem?
You actually have to think about the notion that
product conceptually kind of question fundamentally how
everything works and the team right now is exploring ways.
Where maybe when you open notion for the first time rather
than putting together these building blocks manually you
select your use cases explicitly.
So all this to say it's quite exciting to
be a designer at notion and that we get
to operate in multiple layers of the stack. So the city shape
problems. We think very conceptually we
questioned the status quo of the product. These are
things that are most of the time irreversible and
requires a lot more coordination and
thought with the rest of the team.
You have things like information architecture and
navigation.
Where you're thinking about still high level
broad Concepts, but there's a tactical outcome. Is
it a sidebar? Is it a pop-up? Is
it a navigation form?
And then the next layer we think about are these tactical more
chair-liked problems features that
maybe on its own might not be feel
like much but in some it really
adds up to the end user experience.
And then lastly we have the more
Atomic components for notion the system not
the product. So we think about components like modals and
input Fields General patterns
that we can generalize across the across the
product.
so
I want to kind of end with a deep
dive into one of our projects and the
project we worked on this about a year ago and the
team was tasked to improve comments
in the ocean. And if you think about comments, it's
actually the fundamental form of
communication in notion. If someone sends you a
doc the way you interact with it is to add comments give
feedback engage and in the team environment
like notion, this is the most this is
one of the most important layers.
I would say comments is maybe like a
car shaped problem. It's not quite a chair. It's not quite the
city. It's it's conceptually simple
for the most part, but there's a lot of very tactical
and interaction challenges.
and so
this was an ocean back in 2021.
If you've used notion, you'll you'll be quite familiar with this.
And if we break down the the page
you have kind of three parts, you have a top
bar. That's more textual. It contains core
navigation. You have these tiny
little icons that if you click into shows a
comment pop-up.
And then you have a pop-up
that if you click into you kind of
have to click into out of and it's a pretty tedious experience
where rather than viewing everything in
a single cohesive form. You kind of have to click in
and out so
All this to say the team did some research we explored
the problem space and we distilled improving
comments in three concrete problems.
So the first problem was that comments weren't very
discoverable quite literally we had folks writing in
mentioning. Hey, I can't find the comments and they
really couldn't see the tiny affordances in the
margins. So that was a problem. No one really knew how
to discover these comments. But secondly,
it was really difficult to understand
the intent of each of these indicators, you
know, real might say this looks good, but our
manager might say this needs more urgent
attention.
So there's a problem of priority
in assessing the difference comments.
The second problem was that transitioning between
each disparate thread felt quite fractured.
So you saw this earlier, but when you open a notion comment,
it's it appears on a layer on top of
the fundamental editor. So when you click into it, you
have to click out of it. If you want to open another
thread, you have to then click out of it. So if you
multiply this by every comment by every
page, it really created a fractured user
experience.
And then lastly there wasn't any new affordance for
updated updates and comments in
your document. So if I'm responsible for a document,
I send it out to a few folks. It was
really difficult to assess, you know, when where I
should kind of triage and reply.
So fast forwarding a bit. This was the solution
that we landed on we shipped a two-part solution. And
so the first part was a a
series of comments as in in
the shape of a container in the margin of
your page. So if you use other tools, this
is a pretty familiar kind of experience, but
we also shipped a second part where if you
open a comet's sidebar on the top, right it gives
you a continuous stream of all comments in
your page and this kind of created a separate container of
information separate.
from the core editor
So this is what it looks like an action if
you hover it interacts you
can click into it. But if you click on
the comments icon it then opens the sidebar
and it'll navigate to the corresponding block.
And with this project I really want to talk about two things.
The first part is the Wilderness or the messy exploration
phase what you'll see are a
series of kind of wacky ideas
kind of thing ideas that we played with that got
us to this two-part experience.
And then the second part is all the fit
and finish the polished details that I think
really adds up to the end user experience.
So first the Wilderness when we
first started this project, we were really interested
in this idea of merging these two canvases
the first canvas being the core editor the second
canvas being the commenting experience
and we wanted to merge these experiences as
much as possible. So that's the so
that there's as much cohesion as possible.
If you think about a conceptually an editor, you're typing text you're
adding these blocks when you're adding a comment. You're also
doing something very similar you're adding text and and
referencing a block.
so
The first exploration we were
toying with the idea of introducing a new sidebar
that appeared in your notion editor and this
sidebar would merge all your updates and
comments into a single stream. It's kind
of sorted by time.
And the first this was pretty interesting to think well comments are
a subset of updates. So maybe we can merge everything into
a single stream. But actually when we
were playing with the idea, this is kind of noisy. If
you wanted to focus on each comment you
had to sift through a large list of updates.
So then we thought to ourselves. Okay, what if we
separated out comments and updates into
discrete tabs? What if
a user could focus just on comments and
they clicked into a thread it'll open
the pop-up that we saw earlier.
Problem with this was that well people really hated the pop-up and
it's still created this friction of kind of
opening and closing.
We had another exploration where if you clicked into an
icon an entire sidebar appeared with
just that thread, but this was
very clean in some ways. But it also
showed you it also prevented you
from seeing all your comments in a single place. So we
after some iteration we kind of got to this
form where we had.
Two entry points.
The first entry point was a single stream for your
comments and the second stream was a single stream for
your updates and together. You can toggle between these
two and they would interact quite cohesively with
the core editor you click on one thread it Scrolls
you onto the corresponding block.
So part one of that experience felt pretty
good. But when you close the sidebar you kind
of came back to this zero states where the
affordances weren't quite clear and it wasn't as discoverable.
So we blew this up and we made each
of these icons a preview into a
full comment thread. So that's
when you're reading a document for the first time you can
easily glance what the content of the the comments
was.
So finally just wanted
to highlight a few polish and fit and finish details
here.
So the first
Kind of detail. I wanted to highlight is the page layout
if we break down a notion editor. There's all
these disparate parts that add up
right? So you saw earlier. The first impression
of notion is quite simple, but under the hood, there's actually all
these different components that make up the the editor.
So the first task was to really break down
and annotate each part to the the page.
The second order of things was to break
down the anatomy of every individual comments
thread and comments are
quite tricky because it's form is different. Every single
time. No comment is alike. So you have to
think about the different states of collapsed expanded focused.
We added we
decided to add a preview of the first comments with
the first three lines.
He also think about scale right? There's a comment have there's a
thread have one comment two comments 20 comments.
And all this kind of adds up in really
being methodical about every different state.
So you would think well, if you break down the anatomy of the comment if
you think about the page layout that might get you
most of the way there.
But there's actually a number of keen details that
we have to focus on. So the first detail was
that we had to break the rule of showing the first three
lines of every comments when there was one comment or if
you have a and if you have a long page and you
see a series of single comments, you actually want to see more than just
the first three lines. So we broke that rule for
Threads with one comment.
Turns out that some blocks
are quite tricky, right? So you have this layout and
in traditional text editors the margins
and the content are in very discreet parallel
locations, but with notion,
it's actually quite interesting in that some blocks
can extend the full width of the page things like images maybe
databases. You name
it?
So we thought about what this experience should look like and we
landed in a simple interaction where
if you drag the image or that block
it allowed the comment to dodge
that element. So as you resize your block
your comments would engage directly with
that.
Toggles if you're familiar with notion toggles,
these are specialized lists that
helps you collapse content within and it
creates more organized hierarchy in your
page. And the one of
the problems with toggles is that it hides contents, but
sometimes you actually want a larger entry
point into that.
So we were thinking deeply about how we
might hide the notion content but still exposed to
users that hey there's still a set of comments that you
should explore.
And so we ended up with this experience where the the
content still hid under each toggle. But
the the comments on the right hand side indicated
and hinted that there was more to that
so users could click into the comments and
expand the toggle as another way of expanding the
core content.
Columns notion you
could create different layouts one of them being
different columns and it was quite tricky just
to think through what the ordering of common should
be in relation to the content when it's not
as linear.
and straightforward
and lastly when thinking about the visual
design every pixel matters when adding
content to the page and we
shipped the V1 in 2021 and
we thought well, I think we think we could make this
a lot more compact. So we shaved off 10 pixels and
made each comment thread still
very legible but denser in
some ways.
so
I want to close by just giving a quick shout
out and overview of the team this efforts everything.
I showed today is the byproduct of
an incredibly talented team starts with
our Founders Ivan and Simon
but extends to a larger team of product
designers across three cities. We work
with an incredible group of Engineers and product
managers.
And quick plug we're hiring. So if
you're interested, I'm here Rio is here.
We're giving out stickers, and we're opening
a London office. So we'll love to see you
all around. So if you have a knack for conceptual thinking and
craft we love to talk to you. So thank you very much.